<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN"
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd">
<chapter id="processing-your-first-image">
  <title>Processing your first image</title>
  <para>
    In this section we’ll start with the <quote>hello world</quote> app
    and show you how you can load an image, perform some basic
    processing on the image, draw some stuff on your image and then
    display your results.
  </para>
  <para>
    Loading images into Java is usually a horrible experience. Using
    Java <code>ImageIO</code>, one can use the
    <code>read()</code> method to create a
    <code>BufferedImage</code> object. Unfortunately the
    <code>BufferedImage</code> object hides the fact that it is
    (and in fact all digital raster images are) simply arrays of pixel
    values. A defining philosophy of OpenIMAJ is to <emphasis>keep
    things simple</emphasis> which in turn means in OpenIMAJ images are
    as close as one can get to being <emphasis role="strong">just arrays
    of pixel values</emphasis>.
  </para>
  <para>
    To read and write images in OpenIMAJ we use the
    <code>ImageUtilities</code> class. In the
    <filename>App.java</filename> class file remove the sample code within
    the main method and add the following line:
  </para>
  <programlisting>MBFImage image = ImageUtilities.readMBF(new File(&quot;file.jpg&quot;));</programlisting>
  <para>
    For this tutorial, read the image from the following URL:
  </para>
  <programlisting>MBFImage image = ImageUtilities.readMBF(new URL(&quot;http://static.openimaj.org/media/tutorial/sinaface.jpg&quot;));</programlisting>
  <para>
    The <code>ImageUtilities</code> class provides the ability to
    read <code>MBFImage</code>s and <code>FImage</code>s. An
    <code>FImage</code> is a greyscale image which represents each
    pixel as a value between <literal>0</literal> and
    <literal>1</literal>. An <code>MBFImage</code> is a multi-band
    version of the <code>FImage</code>; under the hood it actually
    contains a number <code>FImage</code> objects held in a list
    each representing a band of the image. What these bands represent is
    given by the image’s public <code>colourSpace</code> field,
    which we can print as follows:
  </para>
  <programlisting>System.out.println(image.colourSpace);</programlisting>
  <para>
    If we run the code, we’ll see that the image is an RGB image with
    three <code>FImage</code>s representing the red, blue and
    green components of the image in that order.
  </para>
  <para>
    You can display any OpenIMAJ image object using the
    <code>DisplayUtilities</code> class. In this example we
    display the image we have loaded then we display the red channel of
    the image alone:
  </para>
  <programlisting>DisplayUtilities.display(image);
DisplayUtilities.display(image.getBand(0), &quot;Red Channel&quot;);</programlisting>

	<para role="centered">
		<inlinemediaobject>
		  <imageobject>
				<imagedata fileref="../../figs/sinaface.png" format="PNG" align="center" contentwidth="5cm"/>
		  </imageobject>
		</inlinemediaobject>
	
		<inlinemediaobject>
		  <imageobject>
				<imagedata fileref="../../figs/sinaface-rc.png" format="PNG" align="center" contentwidth="5cm"/>
		  </imageobject>
		</inlinemediaobject>
	</para>

  <para>
    In an image-processing library, images are no good unless you can do
    something to them. The most basic thing you can do to an image is
    fiddle with its pixels. In OpenIMAJ, as an image is just an array of
    floats, we make this is quite easy. Let’s go through our colour
    image and set all its blue and green pixels to black:
  </para>
  <programlisting>MBFImage clone = image.clone();
for (int y=0; y&lt;image.getHeight(); y++) {
    for(int x=0; x&lt;image.getWidth(); x++) {
        clone.getBand(1).pixels[y][x] = 0;
        clone.getBand(2).pixels[y][x] = 0;
    }
}
DisplayUtilities.display(clone);</programlisting>

<mediaobject>
  <imageobject condition="">
		<imagedata fileref="../../figs//sinaface-red.png" format="PNG" scale="100" align="center" contentwidth="5cm"/>
  </imageobject>
</mediaobject>

  <para>
    Note that the first thing we do here is to <code>clone</code>
    the image to preserve the original image for the remainder of the
    tutorial. The pixels in an <code>FImage</code> are held in a
    2D float array. The rows of the image are held in the first array
    that, in turn, holds each of the column values for that row:
    <code>[y][x]</code>. By displaying this image we should see an
    image where two channels are black and one channel is not. This
    results in an image that looks rather red.
  </para>
  <para>
    Though it is helpful to sometimes get access to individual image
    pixels, OpenIMAJ provides a lot of methods to make things easier.
    For example, we could have done the above like this instead:
  </para>
  <programlisting>clone.getBand(1).fill(0f);
clone.getBand(2).fill(0f);</programlisting>
  <para>
    More complex image operations are wrapped up by OpenIMAJ processor
    interfaces: <code>ImageProcessor</code>s,
    <code>KernelProcessor</code>s,
    <code>PixelProcessor</code>s and
    <code>GridProcessor</code>s. The distinction between these is
    how their algorithm works internally. The overarching similarity is
    that an image goes in and a processed image (or data) comes out. For
    example, a basic operation in image processing is
    <emphasis role="strong">edge detection</emphasis>. A popular edge
    detection algorithm is the <emphasis>Canny edge detector</emphasis>.
    We can call the Canny edge detector like so:
  </para>
  <programlisting>image.processInplace(new CannyEdgeDetector());</programlisting>
  <para>
    When applied to a colour image, each pixel of each band is replaced
    with the edge response at that point (for simplicity you can think
    of this as the difference between that pixel and its neighbouring
    pixels). If a particular edge is only strong in one band or another
    then that colour will be strong, resulting in the psychedelic
    colours you should see if you display the image:
  </para>
  <programlisting>DisplayUtilities.display(image);</programlisting>

	<mediaobject>
	  <imageobject condition="">
			<imagedata fileref="../../figs//sinaface-canny.png" format="PNG" scale="100" align="center" contentwidth="5cm"/>
	  </imageobject>
	</mediaobject>

  <para>
    Finally, we can also draw on our image in OpenIMAJ. On every
    <code>Image</code> object there is a set of drawing functions
    that can be called to draw points, lines, shapes and text on images.
    Let’s draw some speech bubbles on our image:
  </para>
  <programlisting>image.drawShapeFilled(new Ellipse(700f, 450f, 20f, 10f, 0f), RGBColour.WHITE);
image.drawShapeFilled(new Ellipse(650f, 425f, 25f, 12f, 0f), RGBColour.WHITE);
image.drawShapeFilled(new Ellipse(600f, 380f, 30f, 15f, 0f), RGBColour.WHITE);
image.drawShapeFilled(new Ellipse(500f, 300f, 100f, 70f, 0f), RGBColour.WHITE);
image.drawText(&quot;OpenIMAJ is&quot;, 425, 300, HersheyFont.ASTROLOGY, 20, RGBColour.BLACK);
image.drawText(&quot;Awesome&quot;, 425, 330, HersheyFont.ASTROLOGY, 20, RGBColour.BLACK);
DisplayUtilities.display(image);</programlisting>
  <para>
    Here we construct a series of ellipses (defined by their centre [x,
    y], axes [major, minor] and rotation) and draw them as white filled
    shapes. Finally, we draw some text on the image and display it.
  </para>

	<mediaobject>
	  <imageobject condition="">
			<imagedata fileref="../../figs//sinaface-awesome.png" format="PNG" scale="100" align="center" contentwidth="5cm"/>
	  </imageobject>
	</mediaobject>

  <sect1 id="exercises-1">
    <title>Exercises</title>
    <sect2 id="exercise-1-displayutilities">
      <title>Exercise 1: DisplayUtilities</title>
      <para>
        Opening lots of windows can waste time and space (for example if
        you wanted to view images on every iteration of a process within
        a loop). In OpenIMAJ we provide a facility to open a
        <emphasis>named display</emphasis> so that was can reuse the
        display referring to it by name. Try to do this with all the
        images we display in this tutorial. Only 1 window should open
        for the whole tutorial.
      </para>
    </sect2>
    <sect2 id="exercise-2-drawing">
      <title>Exercise 2: Drawing</title>
      <para>
        Those speech bubbles look rather plain; why not give them a nice
        border?
      </para>
    </sect2>
  </sect1>
</chapter>