<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN"
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd">
<preface id="preface">
	<title>Preface</title>
  <para>
    <emphasis role="strong">OpenIMAJ</emphasis> is a set of libraries
    and tools for multimedia content analysis and content generation. 
		OpenIMAJ is very broad and contains everything from state-of-the-art 
		computer vision (e.g. SIFT descriptors, salient region detection, 
		face detection, etc.) and advanced data clustering, through to 
		software that performs analysis on the content, layout and structure of webpages.
  </para>
  <para>
    OpenIMAJ is primarily written in pure Java and, as such, is
    completely platform independent. The video capture and hardware
    libraries contain some native code but Linux (x86, x86_64 and 
		ARM CPUs are supported), OSX and Windows
    are supported out of the box (under both 32 and 64 bit JVMs). It is
    possible to write programs that use the libraries in any JVM
    language that supports Java interoperability, such as Groovy,
    Jython, JRuby or Scala. OpenIMAJ can even be run on Android phones
    and tablets.
  </para>
  <para>
    The OpenIMAJ software is structured into a number of modules. The
    modules can be used independently, so if, for instance, you were
    developing data clustering software using OpenIMAJ you wouldn’t need
    to acquire the modules related to images or text. The list on the
    following page illustrates the modules and summarises the
    functionality in each component.
  </para>
  <para>
    This tutorial aims to instruct the reader on how to get up and
    running writing code using OpenIMAJ. Currently the tutorial covers
    the following areas:
  </para>
  <orderedlist>
    <listitem>
      <para>
        Getting started with OpenIMAJ using Maven
      </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>
        Processing your first image
      </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>
        Introduction to clustering, segmentation and connected
        components
      </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>
        Processing video
      </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>
        Finding faces
      </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>
        Global image features
      </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>
        SIFT and feature matching
      </para>
    </listitem>
  </orderedlist>
  <para>
    In the future we hope to add more content to the tutorial covering
    the following:
  </para>
  <itemizedlist>
    <listitem>
      <para>
        Basic text analysis
      </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>
        Image and video indexing using ImageTerrier
      </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>
        Compiling OpenIMAJ from source
      </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>
        Tracking features in video
      </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>
        Audio processing
      </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>
        Speech recognition
      </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>
        Hardware interfaces
      </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>
        Advanced local features
      </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>
        Scalable processing with OpenIMAJ/Hadoop
      </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>
        Machine learning
      </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>
        Building a bibliography of the techniques used in your code.
      </para>
    </listitem>
  </itemizedlist>
</preface>
